Guide to the Mexico Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Chronological, 1522-1915; Part II. I
  - Title: Royal decree and instructions. Places: Aranjuez and Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal decree dealing with the secularization of parishes occupied by members of religious orders. This decree contains some modifications to a royal order originally issued in 1753. Included is a copy of a letter of instructions from the marquis de las Amarillas to the bishop of Michoacán. 1757 Nov 30 (Box 36, Folder 70, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Ordenanzas del común de los tenderos de pulperías de esta novilísima ciudad para su régimen y govierno." Place: Mexico City. Description: Series of ordinances regulating the location and practices of the storekeepers of "pulperías," issued by the viceroy. Included are regulations governing pawnbroking. 1757-1758 (Box 36, Folder 71, Reel 2)
  - Title: Confirmation of titles. Place: Mexico City. Description: Royal confirmation of titles to several pieces of property issued to Juana Teresa de Cifuentes, widow of Juan de Altamarino. 1758 (Box 36, Folder 72, Reel 2)
  - Title: Volume of royal decrees and orders. Places: Madrid, San Lorenzo, San Ildefonso, Aranjuez, and Mexico. Description: Volume of royal decrees and orders, dated 1758 to 1782, dealing with such topics as the procedures for the sale of seized goods; treatment of prisoners; legal immunity; auctions to supply meat to cities; and the sale of public offices. [1794 Apr 15?] (Box 36, Folder 73, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Noticias instructivas que por muerte del Señor Amarillas...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a report on administrative matters, mainly concerning royal treasury affairs, written for the new viceroy of Mexico, Francisco Caxigal de la Vega. The text was written by the previous viceroy's secretary. 1760 May 4 (Box 36, Folder 74, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Arreglo y método de documentos en los archivos de las oficinas de Vireynato." Place: El Pardo. Description: Royal decree concerning the organization of the archive. 1761 Jan 30 (Box 36, Folder 75, Reel 2)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a royal decree, issued in Buen Retiro on 1760 October 12, concerning the offices of "guardamayor" and "alguacil mayor" for the port of Veracruz. 1761 Mar 26 (Box 36, Folder 76, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Quaderno de varias curiosidades...." Description: Almanac devoted to numbers, measurements, mathematics, and the feast days of different saints. [Possibly used as a school primer.], [1761?] (Box 36, Folder 77, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Archivo general de la nación. Fundación y arreglo " Documentos y obras." Place: Mexico City. Description: Brief text detailing the early history of the Mexican national archive. 1761-1828 (Box 36, Folder 78, Reel 2)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: San Ildefonso. Description: Royal order to the viceroy of New Spain concerning the provision of priests for villages over four leagues in distance from a head village (cabecera). 1764 Oct 18 (Box 36, Folder 79, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Autos para la formasión de las ordenanzas de el Hospital Real de los Yndios de esta Nueva España." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copies of documents related to the writing of ordinances to regulate (govern) the Royal Hospital of the Indians. Included are details of the hospital's history, descriptions of the duties of the hospital's personnel, and records of meetings of the group empowered to write the regulations. 1764-1770 (Box 36, Folder 80, Reel 2)
  - Author: Borda, José de la. Title: "Manifiesto que hace don Josseph de la Borda dueño de las minas de Chontalpa en la jurisdición de R. de Taxco." Place: Taxco. Description: Copy of a manifesto written by one of the wealthiest Mexican silver miners concerning the state of the silver mining industry in New Spain and recommending measures to the king to increase mine output. The major proposal is lowering the price of mercury. 1765 Feb 23 (Box 36, Folder 81, Reel 2)
  - Title: "M.P.S." Place: [Cholula?] Description: Brief document concerning the slaughter of cattle by the Indians of Cholula. 1765 May 22 (Box 36, Folder 82, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Estado general reconocido en el año de 1765...." Description: Brief document dealing with land and cattle ownership by the clergy and lay people in the Kingdoms of Leon and Castile. 1765 (Box 36, Folder 83, Reel 2)
  - Title: Receipt. Place: Oaxaca. Description: Receipt issued by the "aduana" of Oaxaca for payment of taxes on one hundred varas of cloth. 1766 Feb 21 (Box 36, Folder 84, Reel 2)
  - Title: Regulations for the port of Veracruz. Place: Mexico City. Description: Incomplete series of regulations (nos. 35-137) for the port of Veracruz, issued by José de Gálvez. The orders concern the conduct of the port's civil and military officials, inspection of cargos, the collection of customs duties and other taxes, as well as the maintenance of account books. 1767 Feb 8 (Box 36, Folder 85, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Carta de don Cristóbal Hidalgo y Costilla." Description: Two copies of a letter by Cristóbal Hidalgo, the father of independence leader Miguel Hidalgo, to his sister concerning the family's last name. 1767 Mar 12 (Box 36, Folder 86, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Carta del rey de España a la Santd. de Clemente XIII con motivo de la expulsión de los jesuitas de sus dominios." Places: El Pardo and Rome. Description: Copy of a brief letter from the king of Spain to Pope Clement XIII about the expulsion of the Jesuits from all Spanish territories. Also included is the papal response to the king's letter. 1767 Apr (Box 36, Folder 87, Reel 2)
  - Title: Execution order? Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Copy of a brief letter signed by José de Gálvez. The letter orders the execution of seditious prisoners in San Luis de la Paz and public display of the heads of five of the men to be executed. 1767 Aug 13 (Box 36, Folder 88, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Formación de la Villa de los Ranchos." Place: San Luis Potosí." Description: Partial copy of the order naming officials for the "Villa de los Ranchos." Also included is an order to the alcalde mayor of San Luis Potosí to congregate all the families in the district of Soledad in one settlement (town). 1767 Oct 1 (Box 36, Folder 89, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Copia." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Copy of an order concerning a new tax on the sale of corn and other grains, destined to pay for the construction of municipal buildings. 1767 Oct 10 (Box 36, Folder 90, Reel 2)
  - Title: Compendio del cédulario nuebo de la mui noble, ynsigne y mui leal e imperial ciudad de México. Place: [Mexico City?] Description: Chronological index to 495 royal decrees concerning Mexico City issued between 1522 and 1767 by the Spanish Crown. [ca. 1767?] (Box 36, Folder 91, Reel 2)
  - Title: Miscellaneous index. Description: Two page index to an unidentified volume of letters, provisions, instructions, reports, decrees, and other documents. [ca. 1767?] (Box 36, Folder 92, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Ynforme y plan de intendencias que conviene establecer en las provincias de este reyno de Nueva España." Place: Mexico. Description: Copies of reports and other documents regarding the implementation of the intendancy system in New Spain. 1768-1773 (Box 37, Folder 93, Reel 2)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: Aranjuez. Description: Royal order dealing with jurisdiction over the appeals of residents of the Marquesado de Valle de Oaxaca and the administration of justice in that territory. 1769 May 16 (Box 37, Folder 94, Reel 2)
  - Title: "El Doctor Don Antonio Cardozo." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Copy of the baptismal record of María Josepha Venancia, the legitimate daughter of Antonio Sánchez. 1769 May 19 (Box 37, Folder 95, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Lista o nomina de los conventos, colegios apostólicos, misiones que tiene esta prva. de San Diego de Mégico de religiosos descalzos de N.P.S. Franco...." Place: Mexico City. Description: List of all the monasteries, colegios, and missions belonging to the discalced Franciscan order in Mexico, with the names of all the priests, students, and laymen serving at each institution. 1769 May 20 (Box 37, Folder 96, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Papeles curiosos en asumptos políticos recoletados por D. Mariano Fernández de Echaverría y Veitia, Cavallero del Orden de Santiago, Tomo VIII." Description: Index to an unidentified volume of miscellaneous documents dated 1703-1761 collected by Mariano Fernández de Echaverría y Veitia. 1770 (Box 37, Folder 97, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Alegaciones fiscales y por parte de los ynteresados en los oficios de Thesorero, escrivano, y guardas mayores de la Real Casa de Moneda de México: En el pleito executoriado sobre para de los principales respectivas a los valores de dichos oficios." Place: Madrid. Description: Detailed testimonies, reports, and opinions concerning the arguments offered in a lawsuit involving several offices of the Mexican mint (Casa de Moneda). The case was being decided in Spain. 1770 (Box 37, Folder 98, Reel 2)
  - Title: Letter. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Letter to José de Gálvez from the cabildo of San Luis Potosí, concerning the celebration of a "novenario" for the Virgin of Guadalupe. 1771 Aug 9 (Box 37, Folder 99, Reel 2)
  - Title: Letter to the treasurer. Place: Zapatilla. Description: Letter from Diego Sandoval to the "treasurer" concerning the "cuerpo de minería" of the Cerro de San Pedro. 1771 Nov 14 (Box 37, Folder 100, Reel 2)
  - Title: Documents concerning Our Lady of Guadalupe. Places: San Luis Potosí, Mexico City, and Valladolid. Description: Included are texts concerning novenas; a copy of a letter from the bishop of Michoacán concerning the procedures for a city to name a patron saint; and an account of the cabildo's expenses for the celebration of the feast of Our Lady of Guadalupe. 1771 (Box 37, Folder 101, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Elección de prelada de el Sagrario Convento de Santa Theresa la Nueva de esta ciudad hecha en la madre Josepha Theresa de Jesús." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copies of documents related to the selection of Mother Josefa Teresa de Jesús as the "prelada" of the Santa Teresa la Nueva convent of the Discalced Carmelites. 1772 Mar 5 (Box 37, Folder 102, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Don Francisco Guerrero y Zambrano vecino y de este comercio sobre que se le permita beneficiar cera que compró en el puerto de Acapulco." Place: Mexico City. Description: Petition by Francisco Guerrero y Zambrano to obtain a license to process Chinese candle wax he purchased in Acapulco. Guerrero's petition is opposed by the wax maker's guild. 1772 (Box 37, Folder 103, Reel 2)
  - Title: "Elogio funebre dedicado al arzobispo de Valencia el Sr. Azpure." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a eulogy for the deceased archbishop of Valencia, preached by Antonio López Portillo in Mexico City's cathedral. The sermon was first delivered in Valencia's cathedral. 1772 (Box 37, Folder 104, Reel 2)
  - Title: Texts concerning the construction of the Sanctuary of Guadalupe. Places: San Luis Potosí, Valladolid, and Hacienda de San Miguel. Description: Included are texts concerning the blessing of the cornerstone; construction finances; letters to and from donors; and communications from the bishop of Michoacán. 1772-1779 (Box 37, Folder 105, Reel 2)
  - Title: Letter of thanks. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Letter of thanks from the cabildo? of San Luis Potosí to [Luis Fernando de Hoyos Mier?]. 1773 May 4 (Box 37, Folder 106, Reel 3)
  - Author: Gamboa, Franciso Xavier. Title: Opinion on the establishment of the intendencies. Place: Mexico City. Description: Opinion written by a noted lawyer and defender of the rights of the creoles of Mexico, concerning reasons why the establishment of the intendancy system was unnecessary. 1773 (Box 37, Folder 107, Reel 3)
  - Title: "Reflexiones sobres los productos que han rendido las haciendas del Colegio del Espíritu Santo...." Place: [Puebla?] Description: Brief report concerning the haciendas belonging to the Colegio de Espíritu Santo. The report presents the total value of the haciendas' harvests over a six and one- half year period (1767-1773), the total assessed value of the haciendas, and an estimate of the haciendas' average annual rate of return. [1773?] (Box 37, Folder 108, Reel 3)
  - Title: Royal decree. Places: El Pardo and Guadalajara. Description: Copy of a royal decree, issued on 1774 January 17, allowing reciprocal trade between the Kingdoms of Peru, New Spain, New Granada, and Guatemala. The decree contained some limits to the trade. Also included is the announcement of the decree's publication in Guadalajara. 1774 Apr 30 (Box 37, Folder 109, Reel 3)
  - Author: [Gamboa, Francisco Xavier de?]. Title: Report to Viceroy Bucareli. Place: Mexico City. Description: A report [possibly written by one of the foremost experts on Mexican mining law.] The report discusses such matters as a tax called the "señoreaje," the role of merchants in mining, attempts to create new bureaucratic institutions to oversee the industry, and the effects of the reduction of the price of mercury. 1774 Oct 16 (Box 37, Folder 110, Reel 3)
  - Author: [Gamboa. Francisco Xavier de?]. Title: Exmo. Señor. Place: Mexico City. Description: A report to [the viceroy of Mexico?] discussing the mines of the Real del Monte. The report was written by the man who mediated a labor dispute there eight years previously. 1774 Oct 29 (Box 37, Folder 111, Reel 3)
  - Title: Agreement. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Incomplete copy of an agreement between the cabildo of San Luis Potosí and the Carmelite monastery dealing with water rights for the monastery [its orchards?] and the cleaning of drainage intakes. 1774 Dec 3 (Box 37, Folder 112, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter. Place: Veracruz. Description: Letter from Antonio Saenz de Santa María to Francisco Antonio Gutiérrez regarding bills of payment, and liquor sent to Querétaro. 1775 Jan 4 (Box 37, Folder 113, Reel 3)
  - Title: "Cestamen forte dedit illi ut vinceret, et civet quoniam ominium portentio est sapientia." Description: Text in honor of the memory of, or possibly a eulogy for, Lorenzo Ricci, who was the superior general of the Jesuit order from 1758 until his death in prison in 1775. Ricci was head of the Jesuits when the order was expelled from Spain and all parts of its empire. 1775 (Box 37, Folder 114, Reel 3)
  - Title: Land sale documents. Place: Mexico City. Series of documents dealing with the sale of neighboring properties in the barrio of Santiago Tlaxilpan. Three detailed diagrams of the properties are included. 1775-1791 (Box 37, Folder 115, Reel 3)
  - Title: Documents related to empleados. Places: Madrid, Aranjuez, and Mexico City. Description: A series of royal orders, viceregal decrees, royal treasury announcements, and other papers related to employees of the crown. Topics include salaries, the right to the fuero, travel, financial guarantees to assume office, taxes on salaries, relatives who work in the same office, retirement, entry into the clergy, engaging in commerce, and employees who fled villages during the independence rebellion. ca. 1775-1813 (Box 37, Folder 116, Reel 3)
  - Title: Recognition of debt and risk. Place: Cádiz. Description: Copy of a notarial act in which Rafael Gómez, as principal debtor, and Phelipe Montes de Guevara, recognize a debt of 8122 pesos 4 reales owed to Juan Perineo? for the purchase of merchandise which was being shipped to Veracruz. 1776 Apr 24 (Box 37, Folder 117, Reel 3)
  - Title: "Don Juan Franco. Lastiri cavallero del ordn. de Santiago del consejo de S.M. su secretario en el rl. de los ordenes y de la junta de caballería de ellas." Description: Document dealing with the concession of four knighthoods for "naturales" of the Kingdom of New Spain and the procedures to be followed for consideration for the grant. 1776 May 21 (Box 37, Folder 118, Reel 3)
  - Title: Documents concerning contraband. Places: San Ildefonso, Madrid, Villalta, Aranjuez, Mexico City, Veracruz, and Barcelona. Description: Series of royal decrees; viceregal decrees; and unrelated documents. They concern many aspects of illegal trade, including orders to cease the trade; smuggling of liquors; seizures of cargo; sentences imposed in particular illegal trade cases, and contraband with the English. 1776-1806 (Box 37, Folder 119, Reel 3)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: El Pardo and Madrid. Description: Copy of a royal decree, originally issued on 1777 January 26, concerning the payment of the "media annata," "mesada," and other taxes, and their remittance to Spain. 1777 Aug 20 (Box 37, Folder 120, Reel 3)
  - Title: Order of payment. Place: [Tepeaca?] Description: Request from Juan Antonio Estebez to Captain Juan Antonio Ravanillo to pay 3313 pesos to the "comisario cofre" of the church of [Tepeaca?]. 1777 Feb 11 (Box 37, Folder 121, Reel 3)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of royal decree, originally issued 1777 March 3, dealing with shipping from Caracas, Maracaibo, Havana, and New Spain. 1787 Dec 14 (Box 37, Folder 122, Reel 3)
  - Title: "Al gobernador de Coahuila." Places: El Pardo and Chihuahua. Description: Copy of a royal decree, originally issued on 1777 March 14, concerning a dispute over the estates of Antonio Portocarrera, count of Monclova, and his son, Felipe. 1778 Dec 12 (Box 37, Folder 123, Reel 3)
  - Title: "Copia original del memorial y proyecto de Yluminiazn. que tiene presentado Dn. Angel Merelo...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Two documents concerning a plan to illuminate Mexico City at night. The first text is the plan, as proposed to Viceroy Antonio María Bucareli, and includes a diagram of the proposed street lamps. The second text examines the "supposed" difficulties with the plan. 1777 May 17 (Box 37, Folder 124, Reel 3)
  - Title: Royal decree. Place: Madrid. Description: Royal decree by the king of Spain concerning the collection of the "media annata eclesiástica." 1777 Jul 31 (Box 37, Folder 125, Reel 3)
  - Title: Viceregal decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a decree, originally issued on 1777 September 17, stating foreign administrators in the aduana (customs house) could not remove functionaries without approval of the aduana's administrator general. 1801 Jan (Box 37, Folder 126, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter to Juan Ugalde. Place: Parral. Description: Brief letter by [Teodoro?] de Croix, commandant of the Provincias Internas, concerning the mines of [Coahuila?]. 1777 Nov 15 (Box 37, Folder 127, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter and royal decree. Place: Parral. Description: Letter to the governor of Coahuila containing a copy of a royal decree dealing with the duties of surgeons to first cure the wounded, and then testify about the nature of injuries. 1777 Nov 15 (Box 37, Folder 128, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter and viceregal band. Places: [Avanito?], Durango, and Mexico City. Description: Letter from Teodoro de Croix to the governor of Coahuila, containing a copy of the viceroy's approval of the formation of the "cuerpo y tribunal de minería" and the election of its governing officials. 1777 (Box 37, Folder 129, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter and viceregal band. Places: [Avanito?], Durango, and Mexico City. Description: Letter from Teodoro de Croix to the governor of Coahuila, containing a copy of the viceroy's decision that the fleet not sail from Veracruz until January of the following year. 1777 (Box 37, Folder 130, Reel 3)
  - Title: Request concerning the San Jeronimo hacienda. Places: Mexico City and Puebla. Description: Request from José Bernardo de Azpinos, on behalf of Manuel Pinillos, to the group which controls the properties of the banned Jesuit order, to appraise the chapel on the San Jerónimo hacienda. Pinillos wanted to make a bid for the hacienda and could not do so until all the properties and annexes of the hacienda are valued. 1777 (Box 37, Folder 131, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter to Juan de Ugalde. Place: Valle de Santa Rosa. Description: Brief letter from Teodoro de Croix, commandant of the Provincias Internas, concerning the results of a war council and orders given to increase plantings of corn and other crops. Included is a copy of a band, sent to an unidentified priest, charging each mission [in the Provincias Internas?] to plant more corn and beans, wheat, as well as a specified quantity of barley, and to keep certain types of records. 1778 Feb 10-11 (Box 38, Folder 132, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter to the governor of Coahuila. Place: Chihuahua. Description: Brief letter from Teodoro de Croix, concerning the reduction of the alcabala. 1778 Aug 25 (Box 38, Folder 133, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter to the governor of Coahuila. Place: Chihuahua. Description: Letter by Teodoro de Croix, commandant of the Provincias Internas, granting a license for the chaplain of the presidio of Bahía to travel to the governor's home for four months. 1778 Sep 3 (Box 38, Folder 134, Reel 3)
  - Title: "Sobre q. se nombran capellanes...." Place: San Lorenzo. Description: Note from José de Gálvez, minister of the Indies, to Teodoro de Croix, concerning the shortage of priests and presidio chaplains in the Provincias Internas. 1778 Oct 16 (Box 38, Folder 135, Reel 3)
  - Title: "Ordenanzas militares." Places: San Lorenzo and Mexico City. Description: Text in which the first part is an ordinance defining military crimes and their corresponding punishments, originally issued on 1788 October 22. The second part is a set of instructions concerning the duty of "comandantes de brigadas." 1800 Mar 26 (Box 38, Folder 136, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter to Juan de Ugalde. Place: Chihuahua. Description: Letter from Teodoro de Croix, containing a printed copy of a viceregal decree extending the period for the collection and exchange of old money for one year. 1778 Nov 13 (Box 38, Folder 137, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter to Juan de Ugalde and royal decree. Place: Chihuahua. Description: Letter from Teodoro de Croix containing a copy of a royal decree banning a book entitled Año dos mil quartocientos y quarenta published in London. 1778 Nov 21 (Box 38, Folder 138, Reel 3)
  - Title: "D. Teodoro de Crois, caballero de Croix...." Place: Chihuahua. Description: Copy of a royal decree issued on 1778 November 21 concerning the means to seek papal dispensations, thanks, and "indultos." Included are signatures of us officials stating this decree had been proclaimed in us towns in the Provinicias Internas. 1779 Apr 10 (Box 38, Folder 139, Reel 3)
  - Title: Letter to Juan de Ugalde. Place: Chihuahua. Description: Brief letter concerning the incorporation of the office of "apartador general de oro y plata" into the royal mint of Mexico City. 1778 Nov 27 (Box 38, Folder 140, Reel 3)
  - Title: Documents concerning the apartador general de oro y plata. Place: Mexico City. Description: Instructions from the marquis del Apartado to José Ignacio Bartolache concerning the office of apartador, based on a series of questions Bartolache addressed to the marquis. Included is a copy of the decree transferring the post of apartador to the royal mint. 1778 (Box 38, Folder 141, Reel 3)
  - Title: "Sobre usurar en el comercio de platas." Place: Pachuca. Description: Text written by the priest of Pachuca concerning the practice of merchants who advance credit to miners for future sales of silver on unfavorable terms. Another part of the text deals with the religious practices, or lack thereof, in the mining settlements, particularly in relation to observing holidays. Portions are in Latin and there are references to royal decrees and papal bulls. 1778-1779 (Box 38, Folder 142, Reel 3)